Guide to the Connecticut Regional Medical Program Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Connecticut Regional Medical Program Records
1965-1976
MS 764
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
44
(51 boxes)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes of meetings, grant requests, program descriptions, and printed material documenting the origin and history of the program in Connecticut.Task Force reports of the mid-1960s outlining Connecticut's health care system at that time offer a valuable record of medical and dental facilities then in operation. The annual reports and program evaluations issued between 1967 and 1976 provide an ongoing account of the progress of CRMP's work. The correspondence includes many agencies, national, regional and state, which cooperated in this program as well as prominent individuals. One of the important aspects of the collection is a large volume of printed matter: reports, speeches, articles, bibliographies, programs, etc. on the subject of public health. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Connecticut Regional Medical Program
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Connecticut Regional Medical Program in 1976; and Arthur Ebbert, Jr., 1982.
Arrangement
Arranged in eight series: I. Planning Committee, Advisory Board and Executive Committee: Minutes and Correspondence. II. Task Force Reports. III. Program Implementation and Development: Annual Reports, Grant Requests and Program Descriptions. IV. Program Review and Evaluation. V. CRMP Organizational Charts and Staff Personnel Files. VI. Miscellaneous Subject and Program Files. VII. Bibliographies, Articles, and Speeches about CRMP or by CRMP Staff Members. VIII. Correspondence Files.
Scope and Contents
The Connecticut Regional Medical Program (CRMP), one of fifty-six similar programs throughout the United States, was a federally funded, locally-controlled organization. It was designed to work with and through already existing health care agencies and institutions to improve Connecticut's health care system. Its major goals were to promote regionalization of health services and, through cooperative arrangements, to improve the quality, accessibility, and economy of the state's health services.
CRMP originated in Public Law 89-239, which was signed by President Johnson in October, 1965. This act provided for grants to encourage the establishment of regional cooperative arrangements between medical schools, research institutions, and hospitals for research, training, and demonstrations of patient care in the fields of heart disease, cancer, strokes, and related diseases. Supporters of P.L. 89-239 thought that the establishment of such cooperative arrangements would allow the medical profession to make the latest advances in the diagnosis and treatment of these diseases available to the public. They also thought it would improve the health manpower and facilities available to the nation.
In November, 1965, to implement the new legislation in Connecticut, Governor Dempsey appointed a committee of lay and professional health care leaders to recommend a plan of action. The resulting guidelines authorized the Deans of the Yale and University of Connecticut Schools of Medicine to develop a request for a planning grant which they were to submit to the National Institutes of Health. The Deans in turn created a twenty-member advisory board with Arthur Rogers, a Waterbury industrialist, as chairman. Under the advisory board's supervision, a committee of university faculty members prepared a two-year planning grant application. After the grant's approval by the National Advisory Council for P.L. 89-239, the Connecticut Regional Medical Program began operations on July 1, 1966.
From 1966 to 1968, CRMP conducted an intensive investigation of the state's health care system through the activities of nine task forces. A series of program goals and plans of action to achieve these goals emerged from this period of study. To facilitate planning, the state was divided into ten health service areas. Each area commanded a sufficient array of resources to allow its development as a relatively self-sufficient unit of the Connecticut medical care region.
CRMP Director Henry T. Clark, Jr., and his staff essentially proposed to focus on utilizing more fully Connecticut's high level of medical resources and technology rather than creating new facilities and technology. They saw such rationalization of existing health care resources in a given area as the most practical and economical way of enabling medical personnel at the local level to provide optimum care for their population.
CRMP's basic mission was to promote relationships and linkages among the elements of the health care system within each of the ten health service areas. Equally important, CRMP sought to promote alliances between the health service areas and the state's two medical schools, which could provide specialized services not normally found in local communities. CRMP was to function as a convener for the different parts of the state health care system, as a catalyst to stimulate analysis of health care problems, as an agent of change to encourage new solutions, and, when necessary, as a source of funds for new programs.
On January 1, 1969, CRMP received its first operating grant, enabling it to begin the implementation phase of its program. Between 1969 and 1976, when CRMP was terminated under "The National Health Planning and Resources Development Act of 1974" (P.L. 93-641), the program received approximately twelve million dollars in federal funds to augment Connecticut's resources. Typical programs sponsored by CRMP include the following: affiliation agreements between thirty of Connecticut's thirty-three community hospitals and either the Yale or the University of Connecticut School of Medicine; a network of hospital-based, full-time chiefs of service; a statewide blood program operated by the Connecticut Red Cross; an emergency medical services system; and assistance to local communities in resolving health problems through Yale and University of Connecticut resources.
For a more extensive overview of CRMP's origins and development see the bound copies of CRMP's newsletter,The CRMP Story, Vols. I and II, in Series III, box 10; the folders labelled "Historical Background Data" also in Series III, box 10; and the articles and speeches on CRMP in Series VII, box 29. A more detailed listing of CRMP sponsored programs is available in Vol. II of The CRMP Story, pp. 184-189.
The records of the Connecticut Regional Medical Program are significant from several points of view. First, the records provide relatively complete historical documentation, on the state level, of the origins, development, and day-to-day activities of one of the nation's major health care planning efforts. Second, the records document the strengths and weaknesses of one of President Johnson's Great Society programs. They also document problems which resulted from the Nixon Administration's efforts to cut federal spending. Third, the records, particularly the planning memoranda and grant applications, contain information of potential use for future health care planning.
The CRMP records are arranged in eight series which reflect the general organizational scheme of the CRMP files. The records within each series are in their original order.
Series I, PLANNING COMMITTEE, ADVISORY BOARD AND EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE: MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1965-1976, contains the records of the three policymaking bodies of CRMP. These materials document CRMP's major policy and planning decisions.
Series II, TASK FORCE REPORTS, documents the state of the Connecticut health care system during the mid-1960's; prior to CRMP's appearance. It contains the recommendations for improvements that became the basic frame-work for CRMP's planning and operations.
Series III, PROGRAM IMPLEMENTATION AND DEVELOPMENT: ANNUAL REPORTS, GRANT REQUESTS AND PROGRAM DESCRIPTIONS, 1967-1976, contains records which document the implementation of the CRMP program: annual reports, budgets, grant and program applications, program descriptions, and newsletters.
Series IV, PROGRAM REVIEW AND EVALUATION, 1970-1976, contains records relating to reviews and critiques of CRMP programs: minutes, reports and correspondence of the CRMP Review and Evaluation Committee, and Public Accountability Group reports.
Series V, CRMP ORGANIZATIONAL CHARTS AND STAFF PERSONNEL FILES, contains the drafts and final version of CRMP's governing instrument, as well as organizational memoranda and staff personnel files.
Series VI, MISCELLANEOUS SUBJECT AND PROGRAM FILES, contains staff resource data, notably on federal legislation effecting health care planning. It also contains subject files on several CRMP programs: The Connecticut High Blood Pressure Program, The South Central Connecticut Agency on Aging, and others,
Series VII, BIBLIOGRAPHIES, ARTICLES AND SPEECHES ABOUT CRMP OR BY CRMP STAFF MEMBERS, contains speeches which give an overview of CRMP organization and development, articles on the philosophy of health care which underlay CRMP policies; and a bibliography of selected studies and reports supported by CRMP up to 1975.
Series VIII, CORRESPONDENCE FILES, 1965-1976, is divided into sixteen sections according to organization or subject. This series documents CRMP's daily activities and relationships with other programs and agencies. For CRMP's relations with the federal government see especially the following sections: Regional Medical Programs Service and other RMPs, Department of Health, Education and Welfare, and National Institutes of Health. For CRMP's relations with state agencies, institutions, and its congressional liaison see especially: State of Connecticut Miscellaneous Offices and Agencies, State of Connecticut Congressional Delegation, and State of Connecticut Medical Society. The section entitled Outgoing Daily Correspondence contains a complete series of CRMP's out-going correspondence from 1967-1976; it is arranged in chronological order. The material in this series duplicates much of the correspondence in other sections.
Biographical / Historical
The Connecticut Regional Medical Program was formed in 1965 as a result of Public Law 89-239 which provided federal grants to encourage the formation of cooperative arrangements among medical institutions in regional areas. The program conducted an intensive investigation of existing health care facilities in Connecticut from 1966-1968. It began operations in 1969 and functioned until 1976 with funding of 12 million dollars from federal grants and additional state subventions.
Community health services -- Connecticut; Dentists -- Connecticut; Health officers -- Connecticut; Medical policy; Medicine -- Connecticut; Public health -- Connecticut; Regional medical programs; Social medicine -- Connecticut; Connecticut; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Connecticut Regional Medical Program
- PLANNING COMMITTEE, ADVISORY BOARD AND EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE: MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1965-1976; Series I; 8 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in Series I have been retained in the original chronological order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - Minutes of the Planning Committee, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Advisory Board, 1966-1971 (Box 1)
    General
    (vols. 1-4)
  - Minutes of the Advisory Board, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    (vols. 5-9)
  - Advisory Board correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Board correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - Advisory Conference reports, 1966-1972 (Box 3)
  - Advisory Conference reports, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    (vols. 1-3)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    (vols. 4-8)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1971-1976 (Box 6)
    (vols. 9-14)
  - Correspondence of the Executive Committee, 1968-1973 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence of the Executive Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 7)
- TASK FORCE REPORTS, 1966-1968; Series II; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  The volumes of Task Force Reports have been retained in the original order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - 1. Supply and Distribution of Physicians and Dentists (Box 8)
  - 2. Allied Health Professions (Box 8)
  - 3. Continuing Education for Physicians and Dentists (Box 8)
  - 4. Extended Care Facilities and Programs (Box 8)
  - 5. University-Hospital Relationships (Box 8)
  - 6. Organization of Special Services in Hospitals (Box 8)
  - 7. State-Wide Medical Library System (Box 9)
  - 8. Financing of Health Care (Box 9)
  - 9. Research and Evaluation (Box 9)
- PROGRAM IMPLEMENTATION AND DEVELOPMENT: ANNUAL REPORTS, GRANT REQUESTS AND PROGRAM DESCRIPTIONS, 1967-1976; Series III; 4 linear feet (5 boxes)
  The materials in Series III have been retained in the original chronological order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - CRMP Newsletters, 1970-1976 (bound as The CRMP Story Vols. I and II) (Box 10)
  - Historical background data on CRMP (Box 10)
  - Original CRMP grant, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Progress Report for 1966-1967; Continuation Grant Request 1967-1968 and 1968-1969; Invention Statement (Box 10)
  - Annual Staff Progress Report, 1967; Annual Report of Advisory Board, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Request for an Operating Grant, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Annual Statement of the Advisory Board, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Annual Progress Report, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Annual Staff Progress Report, 1969; Annual Report of the Advisory Board, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Annual Report of the Advisory Board, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Progress Report for 1969; Continuing Grant Request, 1970 (Box 10)
  - Revised Operating Grant Request, 1969-1971 (Box 10)
  - Continuing Grant Request, 1970; Revised Budget, 1970 (Box 10)
  - Request for Challenge Grant Funds, 1970 (Part I, Summary; Part II, Detailed Budgets) (Box 10)
  - Request for Challenge Grant Funds, 1970, Resource Document (Box 10)
  - Request for a Supplemental Grant, 1970 (Part I, Summary Edition; Part II, Compendium of Detailed Program Requests) (Box 10)
  - Progress Report for 1970; Continuing Grant Request for 1971; Request for a Supplemental Grant, Summary Edition and Appendices I and II (Box 10)
  - Progress Report for 1970; Continuing Grant Request for 1971; Request for a Supplemental Grant Appendix III (Box 11)
  - Report of the Advisory Board, 1971 (Box 11)
  - Triennial Application; Progress Report, 1969-1971; Grant Requests, 1972-1974, Vols. I and II (Box 11)
  - Advisory Report, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Progress Report, 1972-1973; Continuing Grant Request for 1973-1974; Supplemental Grant Request, 1973-1974 (Box 11)
  - Revised Budget for 04 year (Jan 1, 1972-Dec 31, 1973) (Box 11)
  - CRMP's Seven Year March Toward Medical Regionalization: Special Grant Request for May-June 1973; Phase-Out Grant Request for July 1, 1973-Feb 15, 1974 Vols. I and II; Phase-Out Plan May 1-Sept 30, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Grant Request for First Quarter, Fiscal Year 1974 (Jul 1, 1973-Sep 30, 1973) (Box 11)
  - Grant Request for Oct 1, 1973-Dec 31, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Grant Request for Jan 1, 1974-Jun 30, 1974 (Box 11)
  - Continuing Grant Request for Program Components, Jul 1, 1974-Aug 31, 1974; Program Staff, Jul 1, 1974-Jun 30, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Grant Request for Regional Arthritis Care Initiatives, Jul 1, 1974-Jun 30, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Expanding State and Regional Health Resources: Continuing Grant Request, Sep 1, 1974-Jun 30, 1975 Vols. I and II (Box 11)
  - Grant Request for Health Care Resource Development, Jul 1, 1975-Jun 30, 1976, to Support Continuing Program Activities, Extension of Health Resources Base, Implementation of public Law 93-641, May 1, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Program Proposals for CRMP Funding, Jul 1, 1974, Application (Vol, I, Currently Supported Programs; Vol. II, Previously Funded Programs) (Box 11)
  - Abstracts of Applications for CRMP, Jul 1, 1974, Grant Request (Box 11)
  - Master Notebook, New Program Applications, Jul 1, 1974 Program Proposals Submitted for Revised Sep, 1974 Grant Award Master Copies of Continuation Program Proposals for Fiscal Year 1976 (Box 12)
  - Grant Request for Health Care Resources Development, Jul 1, 1975-Jun 30, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Applications Received by CRMP from Regional Agencies for Funding Related to Public Law 93-641 (Box 12)
  - Proposals Received by CRMP and Considered Ineligible for Funding, Jul, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Connecticut State Department of Health Proposals, Jul, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Sample letters to program directors and hospital administrators re: change in CRMP policy and funding, 1970-1975 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper clippings re: CRMP programs and other state health programs (Box 12)
  - Health Resource Development, Past Performance—Future Promise, 1975 (Box 12)
  - RMP Service Newsletters, 1968-1971 (Box 13)
  - RMP Service Newsletters, 1968-1971 (Box 14)
- PROGRAM REVIEW AND EVALUATION, 1970-1976; Series IV; 6 linear feet (6 boxes)
  The materials in Series IV have been retained in the original chronological order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - Minutes of CRMP Review and Evaluation Committee, 1970-1975, 10 vols. (Box 15)
  - Minutes of CRMP Review and Evaluation Committee, 1970-1975, 10 vols. (Box 16)
  - CRMP Review and Evaluation Committee reports and correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 17)
  - CRMP Review and Evaluation Committee reports and correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 18)
  - Public Accountability Group reports, 1974-1976 (Box 19)
  - Public Accountability Group reports, 1974-1976 (Box 20)
- CRIMP ORGANIZATIONAL CHARTS AND STAFF PERSONNEL FILES, 1965-1976; Series V; 2 linear feet (3 boxes)
  The materials in Series V have been retained in the original alphabetical order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - Organizational and operating structure charts and memoranda Drafts and final version of CRMP governing instrument Staff mailing lists (Box 21)
  - CRMP staff personnel files (Box 22)
  - CRMP staff personnel files (Box 23)
- MISCELLANEOUS SUBJECT AND PROGRAM FILES, 1965-1976; Series VI; 6 linear feet (5 boxes)
  The materials in Series VI have been retained in the original subject groupings created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - New federal health care legislation background data Public Law 93-641: implementation guidelines for Connecticut legislation re: Regional Medical Programs Service (Box 24)
  - New federal health care legislation background data Public Law 93-641: implementation guidelines for Connecticut legislation re: Regional Medical Programs Service (Box 25)
  - Public Law 93-641 Health Service Area applications in Connecticut, areas I-V (Box 26)
  - CUPIS (Connecticut Utilization and Patient Information System): budgets, by laws, and memoranda re: program establishment and funding (Box 27)
  - Feasibility study of fund-raising potential, 1972 (Box 27)
  - Connecticut High Blood Pressure Program (Box 27)
  - Stroke Program data (Box 27)
  - Hill-Burton legislation data (Box 27)
  - Memoranda on New York Medical College (Box 27)
  - Albert Snoke, M.D., consultation service: memoranda Ambulatory care study, 1971-1972: proposals, drafts, minutes of meetings (Box 28)
  - South Central Connecticut Agency on Aging (Box 28)
  - Health maintenance organizations (Box 28)
  - Northwest Service Area Study (Box 28)
  - Add.9/22/82 (Box 28a)
  - "Heart, Cancer, Stroke" file - minutes memos, grant proposals, 1965-1966 (Box 28a)
- BIBLIOGRAPHIES, ARTICLES AND SPEECHES ABOUT CRMP OR BY CRMP STAFF MEMBERS, 1965-1976; Series VII; 3" (1 box)
  The materials in Series VII have been retained in the original alphabetical order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff.
  - Bibliographies
    - "To Improve the Health Care System in Connecticut: A Bibliography of Selected Studies, Reports and Health Planning Activities Supported by the Connecticut Regional Medical Program", 1975 (Box 29)
    - "Bibliography of Articles About CRMP or By CRMP Staff, 1966-1967" (Box 29)
  - Articles
    - "The Challenge of the Regional Medical Programs Legislation," Henry T. Clark, Jr., 1966 (Box 29)
    - "A Challenge to Connecticut Dentistry," Henry T. Clark, Jr., 1969 (Box 29)
    - "The Connecticut Regional Medical Program and the Family Physician," Henry T. Clark, Jr., E.F. Morrissey, and C. Seipp, 1968 (Box 29)
    - The Connecticut Regional Medical Program—from Planning to Operation, E.F. Morrissey, C. Seipp, and Henry T. Clark, Jr., 1969 (Box 29)
    - The Connecticut Regional Medical Program—Past, Present, Future, Henry T. Clark, Jr., 1967 (Box 29)
    - "Health Care Planning," Henry T. Clark, 1972 (Box 29)
    - "Planning for a Library System: Connecticut Regional Medical Program," Stanley D. Truelson, Jr., 1969 (Box 29)
    - "Preliminary Analysis of Internship and Residency Programs in Connecticut Hospitals," F. Lawrence Clare, undated (Box 29)
    - "The Role of a School of Public Health in a Developing Regional Medical Program," Edward M. Cohart, 1968 (Box 29)
    - "Selected Lists of Journals for the Small Medical Library: A Comprehensive Analysis," John A. Timour, 1971 (Box 29)
    - "Shaping the Hospital for Its Future Role," Henry T. Clark, Jr., 1966 (Box 29)
  - Speeches
    - "The Connecticut Regional Medical Program: the Romance and Reality," E.F. Morrissey, 1967 (Box 29)
    - "The Delineation of Sub-Regional Health Service Areas as a Basic Step in Regional Medical Planning," C. Seipp, 1968 (Box 29)
    - "Home Health Agencies and the Connecticut Regional Medical Program," E.F. Morrissey, 1967 (Box 29)
    - "Planning and Organization of the Connecticut Regional Medical Program," E. Richard Weinerman, 1966 (Box 29)
    - Public Law 89-239 Regional Medical Programs Legislation—the Connecticut Approach, E.F. Morrissey, 1967 (Box 29)
    - "Regional Medical Programs," Richard Manegold, 1969 (Box 29)
    - "The Role of the Full-Time Chief of Service in Community Hospitals," Arthur Rogers, 1970 (Box 29)
- CORRESPONDENCE FILES, 1965-1976; Series VIII; 24' (21 boxes)
  The correspondence composing Series VIII has been retained in the original order created by Connecticut Regional Medical Program staff. In most cases materials are arranged alphabetically in each of the sixteen sections.
  - General Correspondence
    - Ackerman, Steven J. (Box 30)
    - American Hospital Association (Box 30)
    - American Medical Association (Box 30)
    - Arthritis Program (Box 30)
    - Barone, John (Box 30)
    - Bernstein, Donald (Box 30)
    - Bibliography, CRMP, 1975 (Box 30)
    - Black American and Spanish-Speaking Students, Committee for the Recruitment of (Box 30)
    - Blumenthal, Andre (Box 30)
    - Blumenthal, Thomas A. (Box 30)
    - Brewster, Kingman, Jr. (Box 30)
    - Carnegie Commission Report on Higher Education and National Health (Box 30)
    - Clark, Henry T., Jr. (Box 30)
    - Community Council of Greater New Haven (Box 30)
    - Community Development Plan (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Academy of General Practice (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Blue Cross (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Blue Cross Series on Health Care (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Health Association (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Health League (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Heart Association (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Hospital Association (Box 30)
    - Connecticut Hospital Planning Commission (Box 30)
    - Connecticut State Commission for Higher Education (Box 30)
    - Connecticut State Department of Community Affairs (Box 30)
    - Connecticut State Department of Health (Box 30)
    - Cultural Awareness Program (Box 30)
    - Demander Bookbindery, Inc. (Box 31)
    - Dentistry (Box 31)
    - D'Oench, Russell (Chairman of CRMP Advisory Board) (Box 31)